### MICHAEL LAFFERTY

Bioinformatics | Human Genomics

#### **CONTACT**

Lafferty.Michael@gmail.com

Website | LinkedIn | GitHub

Raleigh, NC

#### **EDUCATION**

PhD Bioinformatics and Computational Biology University of North Carolina Chapel Hill, NC, 2022

**BSE Chemical Engineering** University of Michigan Ann Arbor, MI, 2010

#### **LANGUAGES**

R | Python | Bash | Java | C++

#### **SKILLS**

Sequence analysis
Dimensionality reduction
Linear modeling
Data normalization
Gene ontology analysis
Gene set enrichment analysis
Colocalization analysis
Enrichment analysis

#### **TOOLS**

PLINK | Seurat | STAR | Bowtie Salmon | Picard | Granges DESeq2 | matrixEQTL EMMAX | Gviz

#### **PROFILE**

I am a PhD in Bioinformatics and Computational Biology with over 12 years of industry and academic experience working in both dry-lab and wet-lab settings. I have a track record of rigorous science, bioinformatic expertise, and clear and concise communication. I love working on complex problems in a fast-paced and collaborative environment.

#### **EXPERIENCE**

POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCH ASSOCIATE, May 2022 – Present GRADUATE RESEARCH ASSISTANT, May 2017 – May 2022 UNIVERSITY OF NORTH CAROLINA, Chapel Hill, NC

- Investigate the role of genetic variation on gene expression in the developing human neocortex (mRNA/miRNA eQTLs)
- Implicate genes and genetic regulatory elements as possible mechanisms for developmental neuropsychiatric disorders via GWAS colocalizations
- Assess reproducibility of human cortical organoid differentiations using single-cell rna-sequencing
- Develop data analysis pipelines for:
  - Next generation sequencing (RNA-seq, ATAC-seq)
  - o Gene expression data (microarrays, differential gene expression)
  - o Genotyping and imputation analyses (1000 Genomes/TOPMed)
- Investigate biological pathways associated with neuronal proliferation and differentiation using human primary neural progenitor cells:
  - Primary cell culture
  - o RNA extraction and quantification
  - o Immunocytochemistry and image analysis

## **PROCESS DEVELOPMENT ASSOCIATE**, Jun 2015 – Jan 2016 **KBI BIOPHARMA**, Research Triangle Park, NC

 Developed unit operations for purification of novel biopharmaceuticals and scaled development purification processes for transfer to manufacturing

# **DEVELOPMENT SCIENTIST**, Jan 2014 – Jun 2015 **CYTONET LLC**, Durham, NC

 Optimized a cGMP liver cell isolation process to improve product quality and yield, and designed primary hepatocyte viability and functionality assays